[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the point of celibacy in terms of practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the point of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because many people are celibate when they're not having sexual relations.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is complete celibacy important for practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can say that even out of the practice of a Buddhist monk, or just in general, celibacy would be beneficial, even for a non-Buddhist person.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the most obvious reason why that would be, is because you're not controlled.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not giving in to a very powerful desire that otherwise controls and shapes up your whole life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, regardless whether people are practicing dhamma or not, sensuality and sexuality, it defines quite a lot of people's lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: It certainly has probably the strongest influence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were to adopt celibacy as a practice, means you would be going against that, against that desire, that pull, which means you would be developing your mind in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as you said, yeah, sometimes people are celibate when they're not having sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not celibacy, because when the opportunity comes, they're going to have sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is to take it on as a determination, as a practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, it's much harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, if somebody is trying to give up smoking, it's much harder to give up smoking if you decide to never smoke again.
[SPEAKER_00]: As opposed to if you think, okay, I won't smoke for a month.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even the heaviest of the smokers can make it, can last for a month.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not if you decided it for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can imagine how much more that is with celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's that's what I mean, that if somebody does have the strength of the mind to come to the point of determining an act of celibacy, means then the mind can start to develop on that level, in that regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, if a person is celibate, they will eventually... it takes time to kind of dry the mind out from the sort of wetness of desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once the mind is dried out, then literally everything else in the life, in the world, that was depending upon non-celibacy, they're free of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your identity, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your identity would fail.
[SPEAKER_00]: If a person who doesn't practice dhamma, say, go beyond sexuality, through practice of celibacy, and they free themselves from sensual cravings, they would, to a greater degree, be freer of their own ego as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the conceit, and all the suffering that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the worry, all the anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let alone if they were to sort of uproot that as well, with the right view and practice of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the whole life, person's life, an average person's life revolves around following desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: And getting what you want, which usually revolves around sexuality, around, you know, finding a mate, a family, the whole thing revolves around the very basic desires, that are deeply rooted, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if one is able to go against it, in a sense of not just pure denial, but in a sense of actually develop wisdom on account of it, like seeing the nature of desire, by not giving in to that desire, you can eventually overcome that desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can imagine the freedom of that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Buddha compared it to being free, like being in prison, then being let out of the prison.
[SPEAKER_00]: Crossing the desert, not knowing if you're going to make it to the other end, and then you make it to the other end.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a huge relief, huge burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, I'm talking even for somebody who's not practicing the dhamma, just sort of doesn't want to give in to their desires anymore, and then overcomes that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would have quite a lot of release and relief.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people won't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, of course, because it's way too hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's way too hard for most people.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's highly unlikely that anybody will do it today outside of some sort of philosophy or religious practice, because it's just... there wouldn't be enough motivation, because it's too hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Back in the day, there were, back in the Buddhist time, there were people who were just practicing for the sake of freedom from desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were not necessarily followers of the dhamma or anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Buddha did say people outside of this disposition can free themselves from these various forms of upādāna, holding, attachments and assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sensual desire was one of them.
But it's not just about
[SPEAKER_01]: Giving up celibacy in Buddhist teachings, it's not just about giving up sex.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just about giving up masturbation or not seeing women or not seeing men.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I read, it's more about delighting in your own sexuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the true celibacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not delighting in your own sexual
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it has to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to start simply by giving up, simply by saying no.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, that is just the first step that you have to then go beyond if you really want to be free.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you have to spend your whole life just saying no.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not freedom, that's just resisting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, there wouldn't be no freedom if you haven't resisted it first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by resisting effort, by saying no to these types of actions, in order to overcome it, then, yes, you have to overcome that sensuality in regard to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to overcome the attitude in regard to your own body.
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude that it's basically regarding the body as a basis for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you see a direct kind of relationship with the pleasure of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this pertains to any type of pleasure, not necessarily only sexual or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any type of pleasure you gain through the senses, you can overcome by overcoming, basically, the attitude of regarding your body as a basis for that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: By appropriating the body, you appropriate that which body is attracted to.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not appropriating the body anymore, you free yourself from the counterparts of your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you're not just resisting anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you go beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there is no need for resistance, because there is no more pull.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, for as long as you're appropriating your senses, your body, you will be pulled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you might spend the whole life living a celibate life, which is good, it's still better, but it's not... it's not leading to wisdom and it's not leading to freedom from... from sensuality.